Guide to the Roberto Sierra Papers
Yale University Music Library
Roberto Sierra Papers
1982-2017
MSS 144
Yale University Music Library
12
(14 containers)
The Papers consist mainly of music and programs. Clippings, correspondence and other documents are also included. The collection should be considered partial, as Sierra is currently an active composer.
Sierra, Roberto
Biographical / Historical
Roberto Sierra is an American composer. He studied at the University of Puerto Rico, the Conservatory of Puerto Rico, the Institute for Sonology in Utrecht, and the Hamburg Hochschule für Musik. In his music, Sierra combines European moderism with Latin American popular music and folk song.
Scope and Contents
The Papers consist mainly of music and programs. Clippings, correspondence and other documents are also included. The collection should be considered partial, as Sierra is currently an active composer.
Arrangement
The Papers are divided into five series: I. Music; II. Programs; III. Clippings; IV. Correspondence; and V. Contracts, Documents and Awards.
Composers -- United States -- 20th Century; Composers -- United States -- Archives; Sierra, Roberto
- Music
  Scope and Contents
  Included in this series are handwritten and printed scores of Sierra's orchestral and chamber music compositions. Published scores include notes and corrections.
  - Box 1
    Folder 1: Tiempo Muerto, III/a, El Éxtasis de Santa Teresa, Chaconne – Éxtasis de Sta. Teresa, (No. 6), Memories of a Rose Garden, Cello [Concerto], 3 Inventos para Piano, unidentified pieces and fragments.
    Folder 2: Suite, Invocaciones, Changos a Ove Nordwall, Mano A Mano para 2 Percussionistas, Cantos Populares, En la más alta del Cielo Villancico, Concertino, Salsa on the C String, Interludio De Noche en Mediania, Es Mensajero de Plata Segundo Acto, untitled piece.
    Folder 3: El Mensajero de Plata Opera en dos Actos, Casi Montuno, Inventando, Vestigios Rituales, Doña Rosita, Cinco Bocetos para Clarinete (Si-b) solo.
    Folder 4: Essays para Quinteto de Vientos, Impromptu #3, Glosa A La Sombra..., Descarga Para Piano y g Instrumentos, unidentified notes and fragments. Kontrapunkt Ülung notebook.
  - Box 2
    Folder 1: Tocata, El Sueño De Antonia, La Lira Overtura, Cuarteto para instrumentos de Cuerda, Sonata para piano, Cuatro Miniaturas para piano, Dialogo I, Tema y Cinco Diferencias a mi querida amiga Gloria, Dos Piezas Breves para piano y clarinete en si bemol, Concertino (bassoon part), fragment of piece.
    Folder 2: Sexteto, Salsa para Vientos, De Profundis, Cumbamba, untitled piece, Descarga en Sol.
    Folder 3: Impromptu #2, Vals, El Contemplado, Piezas Breves, unidentified pieces and fragments, page of notes for Invocaciones, Vestigios Rituales, Concierto Nocturnal, and Memorias Tropicales.
    Folder 4: Unidentified orchestral piece, Memorias Tropicales, Bayoán, Descarga, Bajo el sol ardiente, Dos tonos de verde.
    Folder 5: entre terceras, Madrigal, unidentified piece, Mutaciones, Batata-Coco.
    Folder 6: Tríptico, El Contemplado, Cuentos Concertantes Lenguas Desconocidas, Pregoneros van y vienen, dérive (Pierre Boulez score).
    Folder 7: Conjuros, notes, Lo que paso [mi] las nubes.
  - Box 3
    Box 3 [no folders]: Doce Bagatelas, Octeto Para Vientos, Bongo-0, Sonata No. 1 for flute and piano (x2), Kandinsky, Concerto for Viola, Rapsòdico, Loíza, 2 X 3, Rapsodia, Trio No. 2 (x2), Folias, Cinco Bocetos (x2), Eros, Concierto Barroco (x2), Diferencias (x2), Piezas Imaginarias, Doce Bagatelas (x2), Turner, Tema y Variaciones, Sinfonia No. 1. György Ligeti's Continuum, Libretto for Terra Incognita by Maria Irene Fornes.
  - Box 4
    Folder 1: Introducción, canción y descarga, Mambo 7/16, Beyond the Silence of Sorrow (x2).
    Folder 2: Missa Latina Kyrie.
    Folder 3: Cuarteto para cuerdas No. 2, Mambo Metalico, Tu y yo, La memoria, El Éxtasis de Santa Teresa, Bayoan Set, notes and unidentified pieces.
    Folder 4: El Éxtasis de Santa Teresa, notes and unidentified fragments.
  - Box 5
    Folder 1: Sasima, Glosas.
    Folder 2: Preámbulo, Descarga, El Jardin de las Delicias, Tiempo Muerto, unidentified notes and fragments.
  - Box 6
    Folder 1: Memorias Tropicales, Júbilo, Concierto Nocturnal, Bagatelle – Quodlibet, Omenaje (Lied Para Bongó), Concert. For Orch., El Jardin de Las Delicias, Juegos, (Sueños), Glosas, A Joyous Overture for Orchestra.
    Folder 2: Conjuros, Concierto para Órgano y Orquesta, Canto, Martillo, Los Destellos de la Resonancia, Bayoán, notes and unidentified pieces.
    Folder 3: Las danzas de Sisifo, Alucinaciones (with copyright registration form), La Lira (Sierra arrangement), Diferencias, Alegria, Con Madera, Metal y Cuero, Missa de Requiem, unidentified pieces and fragments.
- Programs, 1982 - 2017
  This series includes concert programs and program notes from performances of Roberto Sierra's music.
  - 1982 - 1991 (Box 7)
  - 1991 -1998 (Box 8)
  - 1998 - 2003 (Box 9)
  - 2004 - 2006 (Box 10)
  - 2007 - 2016, undated (Box 11)
- Clippings (Box 12)
  This series includes news clippings and articles about Roberto Sierra and his music.
- Correspondence, 1984-1998 (Box 13)
  This series includes correspondence between Roberto Sierra and various organizations, including orchestras, organizers of music festivals, universities, and the media. There are a few personal letters included. Correspondence is in English, Spanish and French.
- Contracts, Documents, and Awards (Box 14)
  The majority of this series includes contracts for composition commissions. Also included are financial documents, biographical notes about Sierra, and photocopies of his university degrees. Awards include a 2009 Grammy nomination and several other award certificates.